<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fruteful and a very Christen instructio[n] for childre[n] w[t] a dyalogue wherin the chyld asketh certayn questions answeryng to the same with a generall confession, and the maner of loues, the saying of Salomon in the, vi, of the Prouerbes, and also many godly lessons whiche we ought dayely to haue in our remembraunce M.D.xl,vii. God saue the kyng</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04047</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120421</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855619</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855619</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04047)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 54:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fruteful and a very Christen instructio[n] for childre[n] w[t] a dyalogue wherin the chyld asketh certayn questions answeryng to the same with a generall confession, and the maner of loues, the saying of Salomon in the, vi, of the Prouerbes, and also many godly lessons whiche we ought dayely to haue in our remembraunce M.D.xl,vii. God saue the kyng</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Wyllyam Coplande, [for Rychard Kele],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1547]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reprints parts of earlier primers; see STC 15896--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21120:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21120:1"/>
            <p>A fruteful and a very Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a Dyalogue wherin the chyld aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth certayn queſtions anſweryng to the ſame with a generall confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, And thre maner of loues, The ſaying of Salomon in the, vi, of the Prouerbes, And alſo many godly leſſons whiche we ought dayely to haue in our remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce M. D. xl, vii.</p>
            <p>God ſaue the kyng</p>
            <p>Wyllyam. Coplande,</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21120:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21120:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A frutefull inſtruction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the mornyng at thy vp riſing / thou ſhalt make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of the croſſe ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thus In to this dai do I entre all thynges for to do. In the name of the father, of the ſonne, and the holy gooſte. Amen.</p>
               <p>¶ The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knele done vpon thy knees or els ſtanding ſaye thy. Patet. Aue. and Crede as followeth.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <p>OUR father whych art in heauen halowed be thy name.</p>
                  <p>Thy kingdome come.</p>
                  <p>Thy wyll be done in earth as it is in heauen.</p>
                  <p>Gyue vs thys daye our dayly breade. And forgyue vs our treſpaces / as we forgyue them that treſpace againſt vs And let vs not be led into temptation. But deliuer vs from euill. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶ The Aue maria.</head>
                  <p>Hale Mary ful of grace, the lord is wyth the, bleſſed art thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="tcp:21120:3"/> women, and bleſſed be the frute of thy wombe. Amen</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶ The Credo.</head>
                  <p>I Beleue in GOD, the father all mightie, maker of heauen and earthe.</p>
                  <p>And in Ieſus Chriſte his onely ſonne our Lorde</p>
                  <p>Whiche was conceiued by the holye goſte, borne of the virgin Mary.</p>
                  <p>Suffred vnder Ponce, Pilate, was crucified, dead, buried, and deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into hell</p>
                  <p>And the third day he roſe again from death</p>
                  <p>He aſcended into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſitteth on the right hande of God the father almighty.</p>
                  <p>From thence he ſhal come to iudge the quicke, and the dead.</p>
                  <p>I beleue in the holy ghoſt,</p>
                  <p>The holy chatholike faith</p>
                  <p>The communion of ſainctes. The for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyuenes
<pb facs="tcp:21120:3"/> of ſynnes</p>
                  <p>The reſurrectio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the body,</p>
                  <p>And the life euerlaſtyng. Amen</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <p>I Thanke the (my heuenly father, by thy dere beloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt that this night thou haſt giuen me ſlepe and reſt, preſeruyng me from all hurtes and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>illes.</p>
                  <p>I beſeche the to kepe me lykewyſe this daye from ſynne and all euills, ſo that al my dedes yea, al my lyfe might pleaſe the, for I commit my ſelf bothe body and ſoule and al thynges that I go aboute in to thy handes. Thy holy angell be with me leſt the deuill my ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ary haue any power ouer me Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Thus thou armed with goddes helpe, ſpede the forth to ſcole. or to thy crafte and to thy callyng</head>
                  <p>¶ The grace or blſſynge of the table, to be ſayd of children ſtandinge before it their handes eleuated and ioyned to gether,
<pb facs="tcp:21120:4"/> ſaying thus deuoutly &amp; ſadly.</p>
                  <p>THe yies of all thynges loke vp and wayte vpon the O Lorde and thou gyueſt theim maete i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dewe tyme: when thou gyueſt it them then they gather it, when thou openeſt thy hande, then are they well ſatyſfyed Thou openeſt thy hande and repleniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheſt all thinges liuyng with thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng. Our father. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> O Lorde God our heauenly father bleſſe thou vs, &amp; theſe thy giftes which we here receiue of the blyſſing &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous goodneſe, thorow thy ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſt. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Grace after dyner.</head>
                  <p>LET vs gyue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes vnto the Lorde, for he is right good his mercy is layed forth for vs at al tymes It is he that gyueth meate vnto euery thyng liuyng. He gyueth cattell theyr fode, and fedeth the raue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s birdes that cal vpon hym. He deliteth not in ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſtedes
<pb facs="tcp:21120:4"/> nether ſtandeth his pleaſure in the trompet of men But he is wel plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed with them that feare him and truſt in his mercy. Our father which art. &amp;c</p>
                  <p>we tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke the, O lorde god my father by thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde, for all thy benifites, whiche liueſt and reigneſt from age to age, worlde with out ende Amen. Our father. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Grace before ſupper</head>
                  <p>CHriſte whiche at his laſt ſupper gaue hym ſelfe vnto vs. promy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyng his body to be crucified, and his bloude to be ſhed for our ſynnes bleſſe vs and our ſupper Amen. Our fa. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶ Grace after ſupper.</head>
                  <p>HOnour and praiſe be vnto God the kyng euerlaſtyng immortal inuiſible, and who is oneli for euer and euer Amen. Our father whiche art. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>¶ God almightie, father of all mercy and GOD of al conſolation gyue vs grace to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent togither into the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege
<pb facs="tcp:21120:5"/> or his truth through Ieſu Chriſt that we maye with one minde and one mouthe gloryfi God the father of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt, Amen. Our fa, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶ Grace for fiſſhe dayes</head>
                  <p>BEnedicite. Dominꝰ That meat that goeth into the mouth ſaith Chriſt Math. xv. defileth not a man, but that thyng which procedeth by the mouthe from the hearte, defileth man whiche are euill thoughtes, murther, breakyng of wedloke, horedome, theft falſe witneſſe bering, blaſphemy, theſe defile man. Prayſe ye the Lo. de. Our father whiche art in heauen. et. c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶ After dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er.</head>
                  <p>THeſe are the veri wordes of the holy ghoſt in the firſt epiſtle to Tymothe, the fourth chapiter. In the latter dyaes ſome ſhall departe from the faith, forbidding to mary and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundyng to abſtain fro meates whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, God hath created and ordeined to
<pb facs="tcp:21120:5"/> be receiued with thankes gyuyng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche beleue and knowe the troth for al the creaturs of GOD are good and nothing to be refuſed if it be recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with thankes gyuynge for it is ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctified by gods worde</p>
                  <p>Prayſe ye the Lorde al Gentiles ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gnifie hym all nations, for his mercye is ſpred ouer vs, and, the true<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h of the Lorde ſtandeth foreuer</p>
                  <p>Glory be to the father, to the ſone, &amp;, to the holy ghoſte</p>
                  <p>As it was in the begynnyng, as it is now and euer ſhalbe. Amen</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶ when thou ſhalt go to bed</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </seg>Lye me downe to reſt In the name of the father, of the ſon and of the holy ghoſt Amen, Then as thou dyddeſt in the mornynge ſaye thy Pater noſter, the Aue. and the Credo. with this prayer. Ieſus Chriſt, that this daye of thy ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous riche mercie, thou haſt thus pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued
<pb facs="tcp:21120:6"/> me. I praye the forgyue me al my ſynnes whiche I haue this daye vnrightuouſlye committed in deede, woorde, and thought, and that thou wouldeſt wouchſafe, of thy gracious goodnes to kepe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this night, for I commit my ſelfe bothe body and ſoule, and all myne into thy handes. Thy holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell be with me leſt my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry haue entreſſe in to me. Amen</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>Finis</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="dialogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:21120:6"/>
               <head>A dialogue wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the chylde aſketh certayne que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, aunſweryng to the ſame</head>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>SPeake my fayre chylde what art thou</p>
               <p>¶ <label>The aunſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ As concerning my firſt birth I am a creature of God. endewed with wyt and reſon, the ſonne of adam. and as touchyng my newe and ſeconde byrth I knoweledge my ſelf to be a chryſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> wherfore ſayeſt that thow arte a Chryſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>☞ Becauſe I am chriſtened in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the father, of the ſonne, and of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> holy ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> what i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baptyſme.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21120:7"/>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ It is called of Paule. the lauer or water of regeneration, by the whyche euery man that beleueth is receyued. and conſecrated into the felowſhyp of Chriſtes churche, to be parte taker of life euerlaſtyng</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion.</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ In whom beleueſt thou</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ I beleue onely in God the father almighty, and ſo torth as it ſtandeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ede</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ what is fayth,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Faith is a ſure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence and truſt of a mynde truſtyng and beleuyng in the very lyuyng God</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ How many goddes are there</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The anſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ There is but one GOD alone for
<pb facs="tcp:21120:7"/> all ſufficient, whiche hath his beynge of hymſelf and al creatures hath their beyng of hym</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> How many perſons then are there in the godhed</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ There are thre perſons whiche are god the father, god the ſonne, and god the holy ghoſt. thre perſones in trinite and one god in eſſence</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> what is god</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>☞ God is he of whoſe goodneſſe and by whoſe power I am perſwaded and aſſured through my faith to receiue al that good is vnto whom alſo I flie in all aduerſities and periles, as vnto a preſent, and all alone ſufficient helpe for me, he pacientely abydeth our, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng from ſynne, full of mercy, gentle good, redye alwayes to forgyue, and
<pb facs="tcp:21120:8"/> ſuffereth no ſynne to be vnpunyſhed and that into the thirde and fourth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, vntyll none of that ſynnefull ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke be left alyue.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtione.</label>
               </p>
               <p>☞ In whome beleueſt thou.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere.</label>
               </p>
               <p>☞ I beleue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god the father almighty maker of heauen and earth. And in Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu Chryſt his only ſone our Lorde. &amp;c</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion.</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ what meaneſt thou by the fyrſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere.</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ I beleue tyat he is my GOD, and mercyfull father vnto me, tenderyng me as his dere beloued chylde and to be euermore vnto me an almighty hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> What meaneſt thou by the thyrde fourth, fyfte and ſyxte artycles,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere.</label>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21120:8"/>
               <p>¶ I beleue that Chriſte was concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, borne, and ſuffered for my ſynnes and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to make me righteous</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion.</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ what thyng woorketh this faith in the</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> It worketh in me loue to GOD / and to my neighboures / as to myſelf, and ſo chaungeth me in to a new man ſo that I beleuyng and knowyng god to haue ſhewed ſo excedi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g loue for me ſtudy to do hys commaundementes / and am full heuy i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my heart that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fulfyll them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion.</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ why? what are thy conmaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere.</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Theſe are hys commaundementes.</p>
               <p n="1">The fyrſt commaundeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalte haue none other goddes but me.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21120:9"/>The .ii. commaundement</p>
               <p>¶ Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grauen image nor any likeneſſe of ani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynge that is in heuen aboue, or in earthe beneth, nor in the water vnder the earth. thou ſhalte not bowe downe to them nor worſhip them</p>
               <p n="3">The .iii, commaundement</p>
               <p>¶ Thou ſhalt not take the name of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lorde god in vain</p>
               <p n="4">The .iiii. commaundement</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Remember that thou keye holy the ſabboth daye</p>
               <p n="5">The .v. commaundement</p>
               <p>¶ Honour thy father and thy mother</p>
               <p n="6">The .vi. commaundement</p>
               <p>¶ Thou ſhalt do no murther</p>
               <p n="7">The .vii. commaundement</p>
               <p>¶ Thou ſhalte not commit adultry.</p>
               <p n="8">The .viii. commaundement</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
               <p n="9">The .ix. commaundement</p>
               <p>¶ Thou ſhalt beare no falſe witneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21120:9"/> aagynſt thy neyghbour</p>
               <p n="10">Thou ſhalt not deſyre thy neigbours houſe, thou ſhalt not deſyre thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours wyfe, nor his ſeruaunte nor his mayde, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thyng that is thy neighbours</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ what meaneſt thou by the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> I know therby that I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to beleue, to truſt &amp; to cleue to the lord which promiſeth himſelf to be my god to worſhip and to loue hym alone with all my herte, mynde &amp; powers of my ſoule And that it is he only of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all goodneſſe is giuen me. &amp; vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I muſt flye &amp; call vpon in all my trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, for he only delyuereth me</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> what meaneſt thout by the ſeconde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The anſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Euen as the wordes ſhew playnely for wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lorde ſpake vnto you ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:21120:10"/> Moiſes in the fourth of deuteronomi Than ſaw ye no image or ſimlitude of him, leſt ye diſceyued ſhuld make ye i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages. The voyce of his wordes ye herd but as for any ſhap or ſimilitude of him in nomaner of wiſe haue ye ſen</p>
               <p>ye ſhall not make ye ſiluer goddes neither golden Goddes ſhall ye make you. Exo .xx. Alſo ye ſhal make my an Alter of earth. but if ye wyll nedes make it of ſtones, yet ſhall ye not hew them, for if you ſet any inſtrument of yron to them than ſhal they be defyled</p>
               <p>Alſo this I beleue was erneſtly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken with ſo many wordes, to auoyde all caruyng &amp; curioſite in ſetting forth of images whan Chriſt declaringe the ſame, ſayd. That the very trew wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thei that worſhip the fader in ſpirite and trouth, for GOD is the ſpirite. Iohan .iiii.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Foraſmoch than as god is the ſprit
<pb facs="tcp:21120:10"/> and may not be imagined of our wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, how ſhall we know him</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The anſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Faith &amp; truſt fynde him whan we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in perell &amp; ſhew him vnto vs. And yet this fayth to fynde him muſt be giuen vs for if we get vs a faith of our own facionyng wherby we beleue and truſt in any other thyng than god than ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke we vs an Idole for it is the faith &amp; truſt only in our hertes that maketh o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther god or, Idole for if ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith and truſt be right &amp;, pure than haue we the very trew god but if it be falſe or fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned than muſt we nedes faine vs falſe and alyeng god, for trew faith &amp; god a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ioyned togither with one knotte, ſo that in whatſoeuer thing thou truſteſt and beleueſt. that ſame is thy god</p>
               <p>Here now maiſt thou well ſe, that in theſe .ii. firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, god re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth and aſketh all ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hole hertes and in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thyrd he aſketh our mouthes
<pb facs="tcp:21120:11"/> and tongues to be vſed for his praiſe &amp; holyneſſe of his name</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtyon</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> why what meaneſt thou by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thyrd commaundement</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The anſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Than take I the name of God in vayne whan I vſe it to confirme a lye or to hurt my neyghbour. yea. &amp; whan neither bi it god is glorified nor yet m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neighbour is profited Alſo if I fli not to hym for helpe in my troble, nor take him for my benefytes in my proſperice &amp; welth than take I his name in vain</p>
               <p>Alſo if I entend and do not all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for his names glory than take I his name in vayne</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtyon</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> what meaneſt thou by the fourthe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The anſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ I ſanctify the Saboth day whan I giue my ſelfe hole to here the holi ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture taught me or to rede it, &amp; ſo ocupy
<pb facs="tcp:21120:11"/> my mynde in it. for whan I gyue my ſelf to any other holy workes (or as E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſai ſaith) whan I ceſſe to do mine own wyll or to folow myne owne wayes, al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>though they appere to me right glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe and good, For thus me thinketh, the Prophet expoundeth this point of the law in the .lviii. chap. And for the fulfilling of theſe .ii. laſt preceptes we pray ſayeng. Thy name be halowed, and thy wyll be fulfylled &amp; not owers.</p>
               <p>Thus maiſt thou ſe theſe firſt foure preceptes to pertein to the glori of god and to the halowing of his name</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>☞ wherfore than co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth he the other ſyxe</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The anſwere.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> For our neighbours helth &amp; profit to ſerue them and eſpecially our fader and mother, whom next god we ought to honour to do reuerence. to obey, to comfort to helpe &amp; to folow their godli monicion and inſtruction</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21120:12"/>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtyon</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ what meaneſt thou by the other?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The anſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ That in no maner a way I ſholde hurt mi neibour: but to do to him as I wold be done vnto not to deſyre or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyt any thing of his</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ what? is Thought, than ſynne</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The anſwere</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ yea verely for ſo expoundeth oure ſauyour the law in the .v. chap o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mo ſayeng, That whoſoeuer caſteth his eye wantonli vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other mans wife deſyring her hath committed aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye with her alredy in his hert</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The queſtion</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Than ar we all ſynners, and haue broken all gods commaundementes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The anſwere concludeth</label>
               </p>
               <p>¶ we ar al ſynners &amp; haue nede of the mercy of god, yf we were not all ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the merci of god ſhuld take none
<pb facs="tcp:21120:12"/> effect in vs wherfore the ſcripture con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cludeth that all men ar ſynners that as many as ſhalbe ſaued ſhalbe ſaued by gods mercy only <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>A Generall confeſſyon for euery ſynner broughi into the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of his ſynnes to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe hymſelf with peny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent hert before god, at all tymes. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H my moſte mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the father of mercies and god of all conſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mi god mi father I know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege my ſelf vnfanedly with hirt mind &amp; mouth now before y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> to haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded
<pb facs="tcp:21120:13"/> greuouſly thy high maieſt &amp; goodnes I knowlege, I knowlege mi ſelf to be full of ſyn full of vnfaithfulneſſe, and a ſeruaunt vnprofytable, for al thy ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes haue I tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed and broken Fyrſt I haue not ſet al my belefe, confidence, truſt and hope in the I haue not loued the with al my hert, with all my ſoule mynde and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of my ſoule</p>
               <p>Secondly I haue deuyded thy ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour and worſhip from the and giuen it to the creatures &amp; dyd thinges ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined of my onwne fantaſy</p>
               <p>Thirdly I haue abuſed thy holye name by falſe and diſceytfull ſweryng to the hindrannce of my neybour, and idely and vainly haue I vſed thy holi name I haue not ſayd ne done / nether thought all thinges to thy glory</p>
               <p>Frourthli in the Saboth dai haue I not gyuen my ſelf to hering reding and lerning thy holy ſriptures nether
<pb facs="tcp:21120:13"/> viſited the ſicke &amp; pore confortles / nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſed fro my nowne ſynful wyl &amp; luſt prayeng at all tymes thy wyl and not myne to be fulfylled, wherfore I crye the mercy and deſire the of forgiuenes Furthermor I haue not honoured mi father and mother I haue not ſo moch ſet by them as thou commaundeſt me / ne obeyed them nether conforted them or holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them &amp;c. I haue ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayne, I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue broken wedlocke, I haue ſtolne and boorne falſe witnes. Alſo I haue coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted my neibours houſe &amp; his other go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des vnlaufully. I haue deſyred his wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe, his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his catell / &amp;c. wherfore I crye the mercy moſt merciful father and deſyre y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> for that loue which thou beareſt to thy deare ſonne my ſauyour Chriſt to forgyue me in his bloud: for wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I went about to ſeke the, to truſt to beleue in the, or to doo any thinge to thy glori, yet wold not this luſt &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, this contagious originall
<pb facs="tcp:21120:14"/> poyſon and fleſhly dregges drawen of our father Adam ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re me to do that I wold haue doen thorowe this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall concupiſcence, I ſtryue and fyght daily agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the holy goſt in me, which vnlaufull luſt and deſyre I knowlege to be a greuous ſyn agynſt thy high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without the whiche concupiſcens I can not be, wherfore I being a ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of my ſelf without al rightouſnes without all goodnes, all holynes, all deſeruyng, am come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow by fayth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the vnto Chriſtes mercy ſtole and rightouſnes, vnto, his goodnes, holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, deſeruyng and ſatiſfactions deſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring the O mercifull Father for his deathes ſake, that his rightwiſeneſſe / his wyſdome, holynes, goodnes, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryts and ſatiſfactions may be myne, &amp; ſerue me for my forgiuenes &amp; ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> For likwiſe as thou gaueſt me him to dye for my ſynnes eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo beleue I that thu haſt gyuen me with him all hys
<pb facs="tcp:21120:14"/> to be myne and to ſerue me for my ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacion, wherfore glory, worſhipe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery &amp; rule be to the o father, with thy ſoone in the holy goſt for euer. Amen.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſeuen workes of merycy</head>
                  <p>¶ Furthermore, I haue not giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> met to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gry, drinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirſty, lodged the harberles, clothed the naked, viſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſycke, conforted &amp; releued them in pryſone. For I haue not extemed of how great weight theſe wordes of thy ſonne my ſauiour Chriſt ar, neither be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leued him ſaieng. In as moch as ye ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue done theſe thynges vnto one of the leſt of theſe my brethren, ye haue done, it to me Mat .xxv But I haue beſtoed my golde &amp; ſyluer vpon dead ſtones and ſtockes &amp; haue ſuffred the liuing creatures and der beloued breth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n of Chriſt to go naked &amp; to periſh for cold and hongre. Thus gruouſly haue I ſynned, leuing thy commaundements (oh father) to do deedes of my nowne
<pb facs="tcp:21120:15"/> imagination. wherfore I cry the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy my god my father, deſyring forgeue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the bloud. and for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dethes ſake of thy ſonne my ſauyour Ieſus chriſt. to whom with the be glorie, world without ende. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Thre maner of loues. Fyrſt the loue of god. the loue of thy ſelfe, and the loue of thy neighbour.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this true belefe I ſhal firſt loue god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty that mademe, and our lord Ieſu Chriſt that redemed me &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holi ghoſt that alway inſpireth me. This bleſſed holy Trinite I ſhall alway loue &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſerue with all my hert, mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. and ſtrength, and fere god alonly, and put my truſt in hym only.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ The loue of thy ſelfe.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21120:15"/>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Secondly, I ſhall loue my ſelfe to god ward, and ſhall abſtayne from all ſynne as moch as I may, ſpecially fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſynnes dedly</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not be proude nor enuious nor wrothfull.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not be glotonous nor leche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, nor ſlouthfull.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not be couetous, deſyryng ſuperfluite of worldly thynges.</p>
                  <p>And euyll company I ſhall eſchew and fly as moch as I may.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall gyue me to grace and vertue and cunnyng in god.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall pray often, ſpecially on the holy day.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall lyue alway temperately and ſobre of my mouth.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall faſt the dayes commaunded in Chriſtes church.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall kepe my mynde from euell and foule thoughtes.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall kepe my mouth from ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng
<pb facs="tcp:21120:16"/> lyeng and foule ſpeking</p>
                  <p>I ſhall kepe my handes from ſtey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng and piking</p>
                  <p>Thinges taken awaye I ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtore agayne</p>
                  <p>Thinges fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d I ſhall reſtore agayn</p>
                  <p>The loue of they neibour</p>
                  <p>¶ Thirdly I ſhall loue my neybour that is euery man to god ward as min owne ſelf and ſhal helpe hym all his n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>eitie ſpirituall and bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly as, I wolde beholpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my nowe ſelf, ſpecially my fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> and my mother that brought me into this world</p>
                  <p>The maiſter that techeth me I ſhal honour and obey</p>
                  <p>My f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lows that lerne with me I ſhall loue</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce</head>
                  <p>If I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al to ſyne I ſhall anone ryſe agayne by penaunce and pure confeſſion</p>
                  <p>Here after foloweth the ſaing of Sal</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21120:16"/>
                  <head>¶ Theſe, vi. thynges the lorde hateth &amp; the ſeuenth he vtterly abhorreth</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>Proud loke a diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g handes that ſhead, Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes bloude. an hert y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goeth about with wicked ymaginacions, feete that be ſwift in runnyng to do miſchief, a falſe witnes that bringeth vs lies and ſuche one as ſoweth diſcorde amonge brethren Prouerbes. vi,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Theſe thynges folowyng ſhould we euer haue in our mynde</head>
                  <p>THe ſinnes that we daily do the ſhort time y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we ſhal abide he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e The vncertainte of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dai of our death, The vnſtablenes and frailte of vs. The ſtrayte and fearfull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, The bitter and vnſpeke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able paynes ordeined for ſynnes The euerlaſtyng loſſe of eternall glory</p>
                  <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Rychard Kele dwellyng in Lombert ſtreat at the ſyne of the Egle</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
